Hello, welcome everyone. It is May 30th,
2025. We're in Active Inference Math
Stream
14.1 and here with Jesse Venomstrom
discussing a concise mathematical
description of active inference in
discrete time. This will be a very
useful and epistemic discussion. So
Jesse, thank you for writing this paper
and coming on to you to introduce it and
start walking us through it.
Yeah, thank you Daniel. Thank you for
the opportunity of uh being here and
allowing me to uh present my paper.
Yeah, first of all, I wrote this paper
together with uh my colleague Carlo
Langanger and my supervisor Niad Iay. We
are all in Hamburg at the Institute of
Data Science
Foundations and
um yeah about three years ago I
um started getting interested in active
inference and
um wanted to know really exactly
um how it works so to say but this uh I
had quite a hard time figuring this out
and that's a bit why this paper came
about and um maybe I can I also have
some notes here I can so maybe I can
make very specific my question so what I
wanted to know was okay we have an agent
who has
observations 01 up to OT and has
performed actions A1 up to 80 t minus
one and then what I wanted to know was
an
uh a agent acting according to active
inference what will its action at how
will it choose
that and this question for me was so
with the literature at the time I found
it hard to really pin it down so to say
so that was the first uh main objective
of making that more clear and especially
also making it clear in a way um that is
with in notation that is very accessible
to people who have studied probability
theory or any other type of standard
mathematics and
um yeah and then throughout the process
um a second question came up so that was
the following so um so I will go into
more detail on this later but
[Music]
um an agent has something that's called
a generative model and uh how to
understand that is as follows. So uh the
world we can first look at the real
world and that is uh generating
observations. For example, observation
one the world is in world state one then
uh observation two. So this is all
happening in the
world but then an agent. So this is what
we could call a generative process.
and uh a generative model is as follows.
So this this is some kind of where an
agent has um maybe some kind of
simplified version of what's happening
in the world. It is representing in its
brain and
um from that world from that some kind
of simplified world state it can predict
okay what kind of observations can I
expect
um from this state and this is some kind
of a very similar uh model and in both
cases we can also actually include
actions. So if it acts on the world it
will influence its next world some kind
of simplified world state and the same
also here it will also influence the
real world state. So this is called a
generative
model and
um this generative model it uses it to
um to choose its next action. But then
the second question is how does it learn
uh
uh how does it learn this
model? So um this paper is basically we
can basically divide it into two parts.
One part is called
inference and the other part so this is
we could say also action
selection and another part is called
learning generative model.
So um this presentation will also be um
somehow divided into these two parts. So
I'll first go further into this first
question. How does the agent select its
actions and then also uh this second
later on I will go on to in the second
part how does it learning the generative
model and uh please if anything is
unclear please feel free to ask
questions.
If you're now in the live chat or if
you're watching this later, you're also
always welcome to send me an email or
get in touch in another way. Um, if you
have any questions, I'm really happy. So
I wrote this paper for people in my
situation three years ago
who really want to know the exact
mathematical details of how active
inference is
formulated and uh want some kind of an
accessible easy
overview and um if you have any
suggestions for improvement I'm also
very open to hear them. So
uh yeah so that's the basic overview and
what I have to say as well is that this
is all as you saw also from the symbols
and stuff this is all happening in a
discrete space uh discrete observation
space action space and discrete time so
there's a whole other literature on the
continuous side of active inference I'm
not going into that right now so this
that's also not what this paper is about
it's only about the discrete time um
formulation.
Um yeah, I'm not sure if we already
should stop here for some questions or
that I just uh
continue going deeper into the Yep.
continue. Thank you.
Okay. Yeah. So maybe so one point maybe
I should spend a little bit more time on
it is this idea of the generative model.
So um maybe I write a new one
here. So what I think is important to
emphasize that this these states s are
really uh inside the brain. So we could
say
uh this is really in the brain of the
agent and
um from these states it's
predicting
observations and usually this is some
kind of simplified
uh state of the world and it needs is to
learn these states without anyone
telling it. Okay, so maybe in machine
learning or something you're familiar
with supervised learning where you get
an
observation and uh then it might learn
which state do I have to associate to
it. That's not the case here. So the
agent really needs to learn itself.
Okay, what is a good uh
state to somehow encode this observation
in so that I can do a useful planning.
So this is you could call unsupervised
learning and there is no way of saying
okay the real world for example is
generating observations and therefore
this state should be somehow related to
that uh the real world
state.
Um yeah and to also uh
maybe uh make a bit more clear how it
can be simplified. So for example, we
could have an agent. So we could have a
world in color for example that uh like
there's all different colors in this
world. But for example, an
uh agent that can only see uh light
intensity but no color will have also a
simplified
um simplified uh state of the world so
to say. So that this will only be black.
We don't have gray I see but this is
white and this is
[Music]
gray. So that's just to um just to
emphasize this point. Okay, this uh
generative model is really something
that's inside the brain of the agent and
it can use it to for example plan
ahead. Um yeah, then I'll go back to the
paper. So
um I will start with some
notation. So
[Music]
um yeah so what we are considering is an
agent which
um which is going through capital t time
step. So it starts at time one and um
has also some kind of finite uh time
t and it's performing actions the whole
time and
um
um receiving
observations so that we can also see
here. So we have observations and I'm
using toao the Greek letter toao for any
time point and t for the current time
point. So you'll see that appearing more
often this distinction in the in the
paper. And we can use this subscript uh
with the
colon to uh have like a sequence of
observations for
example. And then very important there's
this word
policy. And actually if you come from
reinforcement learning background this
has a little bit different meaning but
um here in this context a policy is a
sequence of
actions and more specifically a sequence
of future actions. So that is sometimes
I find in the other literature not so
clear but here I want to make that very
specific. So we have a policy pi t and
that is actions small t. So there is
also small t. So actions small t up to
big t. So a sequence of actions and pi
will be then the whole from time point
one. And so usually I write a for
actions that are already performed in
the past and pi for the future actions
that it somehow needs to do planning on.
Um yeah and uh we have this generative
model which we uh write like
this and um so it's a probability
distribution over observations and
states given actions and this uh theta
is the parameter of the uh of the
generative
model. And in this first part we uh
leave this uh theta we leave it out in
the notation because we are assuming
okay it has learned this generative
model and we're just interested in how
it's using it and then in the second
part we will actually look at we will
include it again to see how it's
learning
this.
Um yeah and then also a big part of
active inference is of course that it
needs to infer in what kind of state it
is. So what kind? So it has an
observation and it has this generative
model and then it somehow needs to infer
okay what kind of state could I be
in and um we use this that's also in
general in the literature we use this
letter
Q. So for example an
uh an agent receives this observation 01
and then wants to find out okay or
express its belief in which state it
thinks it is and that we write for
example like
this. So this is the belief. So this is
a probability distribution over states
and it has as information this first
observation and uh in general that's
always or we hope that it's
approximately equal to the true
posterior
um of the generative model. We will go
into this later some more and how it's
sometimes exact and sometimes not. But
for now it's good to uh remember that
this Q is expressing a belief about the
state that the agent is
in and we sometimes so for example if we
uh I can also show that here in the
paper. So uh so this is the the actual
generative model here and here we have
this belief over states and what we are
doing to make the notation a little bit
more concise is to
um write QT for example QT
uh of ST let's
say
[Music]
Um then this T is implying all the
information that it has already from the
past. So this is we can also write it
QST given all the
observations it has made and all the
actions that it has performed.
So this T is just saying okay we include
in this belief all the information all
the observations all the
actions to form this belief so to
say.
[Music]
Um yeah so I think I have discussed now
the most important things from
the notation then we can I can have a
break here also if there's any questions
[Music]
or otherwise I just continue.
Sounds good. Continue. Thank you. Okay.
Yeah. So then we immediately so that was
also one of my goals of this paper is to
immediately get down to this main
question. Okay, which
action is the agent going to perform?
And we immediately arrive there
already. So
um the action selection procedure can be
described as follows. So we have here a
probability
distribution over policies. So policies
were sequences of future
actions. And um we say according to
active inference an agent selects its
next action by sampling a policy pi t
from this
distribution
and selecting the action a corresponding
to that
policy. So I can write it here again. So
we have this distribution for now. We
can uh
uh ignore a little bit
um how exactly what exactly this
um how this distribution comes about. I
will get to that in a minute. But we can
just say okay there
is some kind of
distribution over policies over future
action sequences and we
sample some kind of uh pi t star we
sample it from this distribution. So we
have this pi t star which is a sequence
of a t
star up
to a t
star and then we are
performing this action at star and yeah
you could say forget about the rest. So
this is all right I'll do it like this.
this is somehow
uh we don't are not interested anymore.
So we are only performing this action 80
star and then we go to the next time
step get the next observation and then
we'll do this whole process again. So
this for example this uh a this action a
t + one is somehow discarded. So for the
next time step we'll do the process
again and then take the first action
from that uh sampled
policy and that in a very basic way is
already some kind of answer to this
first question. Okay, how is it
selecting its next
action? And what we see is so it has
received uh these observations and
performed these actions and they also
flow into this this probability
distribution is dependent on this
um on these observations and actions.
And then the next question is okay how
does it compute this probability
distribution? So
[Music]
um that would be the second question to
answer if we really want to get down to
how is it selecting its actions. And
then we see the main ingredient of this
distribution is this function G which is
the expected free
energy and I have written one uh way of
writing it written it
here. Um,
one one question there, Jesse. Um, yeah.
Why is the policy conditioned on actions
from the
past when I don't see the A1 through T
minus one explicitly entering into the
unpacking and policy
inference is based upon the observation
coming in and how that affects the
belief inference. But how does or why do
you have a conditioning on a as well?
So the function g is dependent on
a. So in order to compute this function
g, we need to know which actions have we
done in the past.
Do we though?
Yeah. Because it's but it's a bit hidden
in the notation here. So we use these
past
observations to perform inference
uh about for example here our belief in
future
observations. So in this T here in the
Q it's it's captured. Okay, this is a
belief about future
observations but with the information
from observations from the past and
actions from the
past. It's using those to form the
beliefs about the
future or here for example the same for
future
states or here. So in order to make this
distribution, what state will I be in in
the next time
step? Um it is using
uh some kind of belief about what state
am I in in the current time step which
then again depends on what actions and
what
observations we have in the past.
Okay. So in in practice the B transition
matrix embodies the expected
consequences of different actions but
here it's just written in terms of being
conditioned upon the whole past sequence
of observations and actions that like
would have led to that transition matrix
being learned.
Yeah. So here uh we are assuming that
the whole um that whole B matrix is
already learned. So that we can just
take as
given and we only use this O and this A
for performing state inference so to
say. So we need to know somehow in what
state am I now and then you can go back
and think okay what actions did I
perform in the past and then that gives
you more information about what state
you could be in
now. And I wrote this very explicitly
because often in other uh literature
this dependence is somehow completely uh
not made clear and then
uh I find that sometimes a bit
confusing. So that's why I wrote it very
explicitly. Okay, in order to compute
this distribution we need this
information so to say. So that's why I
wrote it in this
way. Uh does that answer your question?
I think so. I just still I just still
don't I know it's sort of a small thing
but and I I see that that's it's that
you've thought about it. It's just I
don't see any of the
past time steps in the right hand side.
So why would the action have that you
took 27 time steps
ago other than how it influences how you
believe the action to work now? Why
would the specific memory of the action
a given number of time steps ago bear
into the calculation? Now,
so for example, if we take this
distribution, right, which is uh our
belief in what state we will be in in
the next time
step then it I think there's many uh
situations where that we can think of
that it's relevant what I did to steps
two time steps before. So for example,
if two hours ago I decided to fly to
Germany, then that will still have
influence on where I will be maybe the
next
hour. But like in a grid world example,
if the transition matrix is the up,
down, left, right, the fact that you
moved a certain way 25 time steps
ago doesn't need to specifically come
into
play when you're thinking about the next
consequences of your
action. So let's say we have a grid
world
uh which is just 1D. let's
say 1D grid world and you can go left or
left or
right. Those are the two
actions.
Um, and let's say this agent knows I'm
always starting in uh location zero.
And
um let's say it uh or let's say
differently here. Let's say here zero.
That's a bit
easier. And then
[Music]
um every action you did in the past will
have an influence on in what
location you're in
now. Right? If I for example we are now
at t = 3 then your location will be
different if a1 is
left compared to if a1 is
right. But is it conditioned upon your
current location and the consequences of
action from your current location only
or is it specifically conditioned upon
an action that you took in a past moment
other than how that action resulted in
you getting to where you are
now? Ah maybe I sorry that took maybe
long. So these actions are really the
actions we performed in the past. So not
any random actions but really only the
one that we performed in the
past. Is that your question or
the past? Yeah, I we we can continue. I
just I see the past actions matter for
changing where you are and if you're
able and and you could do other
learnings and so on
but the past actions themselves don't
influence where you are or your beliefs
about the consequences of action which
are all that come into play in the
operational calculation of G
which doesn't specifically invoke a
later okay yeah we can maybe uh
we can maybe postpone it to later to see
if we can uh yeah make it uh more
clear. So um yeah so maybe to get back
to the to the
uh so we wanted to know okay what is
this what will be the next action then
we saw okay there's this distribution
uh that we sample policies
from and uh from there we take the first
action and that will be our action and
then we are Now looking at okay what is
this function g that is used for
uh for uh computing this um probability
distribution and that function g uh
looks a little bit complicated. So we
can just now uh see what is all coming
in to compute this
uh this probability distribution. So we
see um there is this uh this
distributions Q which are our beliefs
about future states and future
observations. So those are and we will
discuss later exactly how it can uh
derive these uh distributions and they
are all dependent on our policies or the
next possible actions. So for each
different policy we'll also have
different beliefs about what
observations we could uh get in the
future.
So those are the main ingredients here.
And then we have this distribution
PC which is a preference distribution of
the agent. And this preference
distribution I also wrote it here. It's
completely distinct from the generative
model P. So it has nothing to do so P is
a certain distribution and then PC is a
very different distribution. And so they
have nothing to do with each other in
that sense but it is a an ingredient for
computing this uh expected free
energy.
Um yeah maybe also nice to see. So for
example this
uh distribu this distribution also in
the paper of uh lens costa and others uh
we see it here in equation 10. So he
also describes it here and actually we
don't see it it's just a black bar.
Oh, that's But you do see the
notes,
right? Now it's just the tabs.
And
now, yeah, still just the
tabs.
Um, this weird. Yeah. Maybe reshare the
screen. Yeah.
Did something change or not? Yep. Okay,
now we see the paper. Okay, great. Sorry
about that. Oh, good. And now you see
the notes. Yep.
And now you see the other paper. There
we go. There we go. Yeah. So, this is
the paper of Lens D Costa and others.
and he has here the same um distribution
uh over
policies and then actually in Thomas
Par's book and others
um there the distribution is a bit more
complicated they also have an E and an F
term and I'm writing in the paper uh I'm
was planning not to go into that now but
I'm writing in the paper here also a
note on why um they have those
terms. But then you can at least see
okay um this uh you can find this
distribution in these I use those two as
main
sources for writing this
paper. Um yeah so let's so maybe people
who have already studied some active
inference are more familiar with what
comes now but I thought just to briefly
discuss uh this expected free energy and
how you can think of
it. So
um we have the equation here and we see
that there are two terms and this first
term is an uh KL divergence between two
distributions and this first
distribution is distribution over our
beliefs in what state we will be in in
the future given that we have some
observations
that which observations are again
appearing here and we compare this
distribution. So the beliefs about
states given that we have already the
observations with this distribution
where we don't have the
observations and um so what you could
say a little bit is if these
observations are very
informative then our belief about the
state will be very different from when
we don't have the uh observations.
S so then this difference will be
large. But if these observations are not
so informative then these two
distributions will be pretty similar and
then this difference will be small. So
the size of this difference says okay
how informative will these future
observations
be? And these future observations depend
again on the policy. So we somehow take
an average over what future observations
do we expect given that we have this as
next actions and given that we already
have some observations and actions done
in the
past. Um so this first term is called
epistemic value of information or
information
gain. And then uh this second term we
see this preference distribution here
come up. So this is the
observations that the u agent would
really like to make and the distribution
here is um the observations that it
thinks it will make if it is going to do
these
actions. And so
um the higher this is basically the more
likely this
uh policy will give observations that it
actually wants to have. So we want this
um and that we see
also if we go back to this equation. So
we see the lower the expected free
energy of a policy the more likely it is
that we will sample that policy. And we
also see that
uh the
higher these two terms are because of
this minus sign the lower the expected
free energy will be. So we want both
this utility and the information gain.
We want it to be high for a specific
policy or those are policies that we are
likely the agent is likely going to
sample. Um so that is one way to think
about the expected free energy and then
another equivalent way of writing it is
the following.
So here we actually don't have this
minus sign. So these terms we both want
them to be small or the uh the smaller
they are the more likely that policy is
going to be
sampled. And this term here is an
entropy. And it's basically
um looking at the
entropy or you could also say
uncertainty about the
observation if the agent knows the state
it's in.
So if it's in a certain
state but
um even though it knows what state it's
in it is very hard for the uh agent to
predict what the observation will be.
then this entropy will be high and then
so therefore also this ambiguity will be
high and therefore the agent prefers to
be in um states that have low ambiguity.
So that's this first term and then the
second term is again a KL divergence but
this time
between the uh belief uh that the agent
has about its future observations given
a certain
policy compared to the observations it
actually wants to have. So if this
difference is big then it believes it
will get different observations from the
ones that it wants to have. So that you
could say is bad. So this term which is
called the expected complexity or
risk those uh
um we we want it to be
small. So that's a little bit of
interpretation on this
um on this term uh on this G that is
used for calc for computing the
distribution for sampling the policies
and therefore the
actions. So there is
[Music]
um one more thing is that we can that is
for the computation nice. So we can make
some kind of approximations. We will
come back to that later as well in some
more detail. And then this G actually we
can write it as a sum of different uh of
like single time step G
ts and that makes all the computations a
bit
easier and um I know that there's much
more to write or to say about this
expected free energy and where it comes
from but I think that was not the aim
really of this paper. So then I refer
you to these uh other
sources.
Um yeah. So now we have discussed this
distribution where the policies are
sampled from. We have discussed this G.
But then an important
ingredient of this G of computing this G
are these uh distributions Q QT. So this
belief about future or about states and
about
observations and also in the actual
often we are actually interested in
these so not over a sequence of states
but just over one specific time point
towel and um I was actually thinking for
this podcast not to go into this too
much because I think it's
relatively straightforward. So, um at
least what I write
here because I think my uh I think uh
the philosophy of this whole approach is
that we want to use some kind of basian
um basian approach as much as possible.
And what I have done here is just
describe exact basian inference which
would be somehow the simplest way of
forming beliefs about states and
observations. And then actually in more
advanced literature so to say you could
say that is some kind of an
approximation of this uh exact basian
inference. So I would say you could read
through this. I can maybe uh show one
small example. So we have this
um generative model
over
observations and
states
given
actions. And you could also write this
model
uh in this way.
[Music]
And there we see that this model
factorizes. So maybe I can just use what
I already wrote down. So we see that we
can really somehow decompose it into
very simple elements where we have a
prior over the first observation. This
one
um we have a distribution that is
telling us okay if we are in a certain
state and we perform a certain action
what state will be the next
one and we have a distribution that is
saying okay if we are in a certain state
what observation do we expect to get. So
those are the three ingredients which
are also often referred to as the
um maybe I write on this
also. So this is called the usually
called the B matrix. This is called the
A matrix and this I think usually a D
vector or something this
prior. So those are the three
ingredients for this generative model.
And then for example, so how you would
perform
um exact patient inference is for
example we say okay we so we first can
express our belief in what state we are
in we can just use okay that's the
prior which we assumed we already had
and
then we then get an observation.
So that's why this that one is referring
to and that we want in this case to be
the exact posterior
S1 given
O1 which is proportional to
uh O1 given
S1 and our so this is this uh A
matrix and the prime higher or our
belief, let's say that's maybe more
general, our
belief about what state we were in
before receiving this
observation. So this is a very simple
example of belief updating so to say
which I describe in more detail here in
the paper. And I think if you're just
starting out with active inference, I
think it's quite nice to just think
about this whole state inference in this
way and think of these other approaches
like uh minimizing some kind of
variation of free energy as some kind of
approximations to just doing this exact
patient inference.
Um yeah and that basically concludes all
the
ingredients we need for describing how
an agent is uh
performing its next actions or how it's
choosing which next action it's
taking. And u so I'm skipping now over
this learning part. We will get into
that a little
bit. And then here in section four there
is a completely worked out example. So I
really recommend so you've might also
seen this uh in for example Thomas Par's
book. Um I've tried to make it very
explicit here and very precise that you
can really follow exactly what is
happening and I invite you to just go
through this example. So this up till
here is just some kind of definition of
the model and then um here we say okay
how it's performing
uh the inferences how it's making these
cues and then here we see we compute the
expected free energy for all different
policies. So this is the first action
this is the second action. So we walk
somehow through a an example episode of
this mouse in this T-mase
um uh which is acting according to
active inference and then second time
step it's updating its beliefs and then
again computing expected free energy and
then again uh selecting sampling a
policy and its action.
So
um yeah so I invite you to go through
that as well and
um what I found hard so um I looked at
this
um there is also so in order to compute
make these computations I thought okay I
really want to uh uh make the
computations so I looked into this um
library py mdp and also a a little bit
at the other one SPM I think um which is
written in
MTLOP but what I found hard was that in
both code bases the actual
computations of what's really going on
are very deep uh uh down in the code so
to say so are not so
accessible and what I did was actually
um to uh to write my own code to do the
op to do the these
calculations which is also uh available
on GitHub. So here on the first page is
the GitHub link and I can and what I
think is relatively nice from this code
is that it's very so you see the code
right?
Yep. Yeah. Um so that it's relatively
easy to read. So for example there's a
function sample action which is exactly
and I have also tried to refer to all
the equations in the paper. So for
example here this is the first equation
we've been talking about this uh
distribution over
policies and here you see exactly how
it's computed. So we have to compute for
every policy the expected free energy
and in order to have the expected free
energy we need these beliefs over states
and then we have to take this soft max
function. Oh, I did not actually say
anything about so this this zigma here
that's maybe good to just clarify this
is the soft max function which makes um
just these values. So we get for every
pi we get a different value makes these
values into a probability
distribution.
Um so for every pi we have a different
uh expected free energy. We make it into
a probability distribution and then we
sample from it and then we take the
first element basically of the policy
which is our action and then we return
the
action. So I think this code so if
you're just interested you can play
around with it. you can take some parts
of it. You can do with it whatever you
want. But if maybe if the maths are not
so clear for you, but it's more clearer
in code. Then um you can also have a
look at this. So it's has the same kind
of sequence as the paper. So we sample
an action. How's the expected energy
computed? We need these two things info
gain and utility. And here we have a
part about how it's
um updating its beliefs and that's
exactly the same as what we uh what is
described here in the state inference.
So this is a little bit different for
example from the PMDP and um and SPM
where they use more advanced methods for
doing this state inference. But for easy
examples, I think this is really more
than enough just to get an very precise
idea of what is really happening. And
then there's also uh functionality for
learning which we will go into
now. So I think that's everything I
wanted to say at least from my side
about the
inference. So maybe uh if there's any
questions I'm very happy to go into
those now.
Okay, I could uh maybe maybe finish
covering all the sections of the paper
and then there's a few questions in the
live chat and people can add some more.
Okay.
Yeah. So for the second part learning
um
I was thinking to actually go a little
bit more or
to make it a bit more difficult so to
say and really go into depth of uh where
the equations come
from because uh for a long time that was
actually also unclear to me and actually
quite late in the process. It became
exactly clear of how
um where the the equations for learning
come from. And um I think that's also a
quite a relevant or significant
contribution of this paper of this paper
to uh present that and I thought it
might be nice for the people who are
interested also in where they come from
to go in to a little bit more
depth
now. So I would actually say that we go
then to the appendix. So there's here
appendix B
um and we actually first look at a
little bit simpler setting to somehow
get familiar with the basics and then we
go back to this setting of an agent
operating in a
world.
[Music]
Um yeah maybe I introduce it a little
bit here in the notes. though I'm
slightly changing notation now to
uh avoid confusion but maybe it also
makes it a bit more complex. I don't
know. So we have now um X and
Z and you could basically think of X as
an
observation and Z as a
[Music]
uh latent state I call it. So
um and maybe I just I think in most
cases you can also
think about this as the
O and this about the S so to say of the
of the
model.
Um but that doesn't always hold. So
that's why I chose to uh call it X and
Z.
And we first for now forget completely
about this uh about this Z. And we uh
imagine some kind of very simplistic
setting where we want to where we are
receiving observations
X and we want to somehow make a model of
these received observations. So we want
to make some kind of probability
distribution X.
I'm checking which notation
exactly I'm using.
Yeah. So there's some different
observations we can make. uh one up to
n. And we want to model
um the observations we make with a
probability
distribution which is dependent on theta
and then very specifically. So it is
just the probability that we see an
observation I given theta is theta
I
low. Um so theta is a vector from uh
theta 1 up to theta
n. And um the learning and then you
could say learning is finding this
theta and um what uh the active
inference uh literature is suggesting is
to think of this theta also. So that is
a very basian kind of approach that we
think of this theta also as something
that we can have a belief about. So we
uh on
its so we can have also a probability
distribution over the theta which is
somehow expressing okay I believe my
belief about the theta uh that theta i
is 0.1 for example is uh is this
number and that is again so I'm going to
use the bar
here Um that is again dependent on some
kind of hyperparameter
alpha and um this distribution is called
the dirishle
distribution which is a
product over the theta i that we raise
to the
power alpha minus one and so alpha is
also an vector from
uh alpha 1 up to alpha
n. So this distribution and by the way
there's another paper from Ryan Smith I
think it's also in the references which
also describes this gives a little bit
more intuition uh about this whole
process which I think is really nice. So
I can also recommend uh looking at
that.
[Music]
Um yeah, but so this is basically
describing our beliefs about our
parameters and then just so we could say
the prior
belief and then um we can for example we
make a specific observation
XAR and then we can ask ourselves
How is this
uh belief going to change if we
incorporate this new information that we
made a certain
observation and that I'm not going to
all write down but we can
u look at
here
let's
here so what I just described was this
so Uh we have this um
distribution uh parameterized and this
belief about our
theta and then we are interested in this
posterior belief so to say after having
this made this observation
XAR and
um what we can if you work that
out you see that that's again a dish
distribution
ution but then uh with a different
alpha. So we call the updated uh alpha
we call it alpha prime. And uh this
[Music]
um this thing here is the indicator
function which is basically um which is
one when xar is equal to x i and zero
otherwise. So what is happening is that
we increase uh the alpha i by one which
corresponds exactly to the observation
to the i of the observation and the rest
of the alpha stays the same. And if we
look again at this definition of the
dishlay distribution. So we see the
higher the alpha the more weight um that
theta i is going to get in the
probability
distribution. So this is a very I would
say elegant way of updating your beliefs
about the theta
uh when you get new
observations. And this is the general
idea of how the theta is also learned in
the setting um that we are looking at in
this uh pom dp this partially observed
mark of decision process setting where
we have
states so hidden states uh observations
and
actions.
[Music]
Um
yeah, but so what we were looking at
here was just a setting where we had
just observations but we didn't have any
latent
states and now the question is what
happens when we do include latent
states. So we can do a similar
derivation. So we now have two
distributions
uh depending parameterized by two
different thetas. So we have a prior
which is a vector over the latent states
and then we have some kind of matrix
which is saying okay given we have a
certain latent state what's the
probability of a certain
observation and
[Music]
um then we can again ask ourselves this
question
um what happens with our
belief over theta
Yeah, if we get an extra
observation and what is actually
uh the case here is that we get some
kind of very complicated distribution
which is not
uh a dearish
distribution.
Um so this exact
method is not so useful for updating. So
this is more like the setting we uh we
are looking at right where we have
observations and latent states.
Um so we have to do something slightly
different and uh that is uh that we do
by the mean field
approximation and
um so what we do instead is we
um
uh let's see what how I can
best
[Music]
continue. So
maybe I go very brief briefly to
appendix A. So in appendix A I
uh describe some kind of very general.
So I think most of you have already seen
this but just for the completeness
uh a variational free energy
minimization
approach. So
[Music]
um it's described here. So we have some
kind of uh joint
distribution and we want to
uh um compute a posterior which is also
the setting we had
before.
Um but often this
uh posterior is hard to compute
directly. So what we do then is we
instead
uh choose a family of distributions
Q and
um
find so this Q tildas are all element of
this Q and we try to find uh that Q
tilda that is minimizing this
expression and that Q Q we call qx
because it's actually depend dependent
on this X on the observation that we
made and this is some kind of very
general approach which is called the
variational
approach and that is somehow used to
approximate a posterior that we can't uh
compute directly. So that is described
in more detail here in this appendix and
also how it plays a role in active
inference.
Um I think for time reasons I won't go
into that much deeper now but just to
describe this method at least. So we use
that same method also here. So right now
we were dealing with latent states. So
these zetss that we don't know and we
are dealing with the parameters that we
don't know. So we somehow uh but what we
do know is the observation and the
hyperparameters and we want to find the
distribution over the latence and the
parameters. And then we use the same uh
variational free energy minimization
approach where we are trying to find the
Q that is minimizing this
distribution. And then what we do what I
was also saying before often we restrict
the cues that we can choose from which
is uh and in this case we uh are only
looking at Q's which can be written as a
product of these individual
distributions. So that's some kind of an
approximation that we are making
here which is called a mean field
approximation.
And um if we do
that then
um this
uh
this equation simplifies a
bit and what we also do so this is um
very important insight is that it's
quite hard to minim ize both of these
cues at the same time because they are
both influencing each other. And there
is a specific algorithm called the Kafi
algorithm coordinate ascent variational
inference algorithm which is saying okay
instead of trying to find both at the
same time we start by fixing one and
then optimizing the other and then use
that. Uh so for example we start by
fixing this q theta and then find qz and
then use this newly found qz to find an
q d theta and then you can do that
iteratively and hopefully get uh to the
optimizer and that is also exactly the
approach that is used for learning in
the active inference. So very
specifically we first have some kind of
prior belief about our generative model
about the parameters of the generative
model. So we fix those uh that belief so
to say or those parameters and with
those parameters with the generative
model we can uh do inference like uh we
looked at before like this basian uh
basian inference and that's also what's
done here. So we uh get some kind of qz.
So that is so this is a different way of
describing inference in terms of
variation of free energy but what's
basically what's done here is we are
just trying to infer what kind of latent
state are we and we have fixed the
parameters Q
theta so and then we have this uh qz so
this belief about the state we are in
and then we are somehow where we want to
be We want to to find this distribution
uh Q theta and then we use this this
fixed
QZ to then
optimize this distribution which is only
dependent somehow on Q theta and the QZ
is
fixed. And if you would really want to
find the minimizer, you would
continuously be doing this alternating
these two
steps.
[Music]
Um and um what is very important to note
here is that uh the active inference
literature is saying our update is only
doing the first step. So we only do the
first step. We do one time state
inference and one time uh we
optimize uh this parameter believe on
the parameter given this state inference
and then we stop. So that is so it's not
exactly the same as the kafi algorithm
but you could say it's only the first
step of the kafi
algorithm and
um
so here I'm describing what does that
minimizer then look like and that is
given by this
um basically the exponent of the term
that's here. So you can also see that if
we take the exponent and we take the log
we just get what's there and then it's
minus what's there. So that is the
minimizer so to say and I'm using these
terms C with the backslash to say okay
these are all terms independent of the
argument so we don't have to worry about
them for the
minimization. So here we have a very
specific form of the updated
belief in our
parameter. And
um then we can use the fact that we are
actually working with this this uh de
slay prior and this categorical
model and then we can so that p here
that was defined here. So in terms of
these
thetas and in terms of these
durishlays and what you see then is that
this uh updated Q after the first step
in this algorithm
uh looks like this and this is exactly
again a deishlay distribution. So that's
a really nice result. So I didn't make
any assumption that it has to be a
deishlay distribution. I only said okay
we do this mean field
approximation but it comes out that it
is if you only do the mean field
approximation that this first step of
the cafe algorithm is again a dear slay
distribution. So we can um formulate the
update again in a very elegant way like
this. So we just add something to these
two updated
alphas and what we add exactly is the
following. So for example this uh alpha
d is related to the theta d which is
[Music]
um um which is the belief about the the
prior belief in the latent
state and we add
um we add the belief after uh doing the
inference that we are in state. So this
is in some sense a very similar update
to this update here where we are just
adding one for the observation that we
did but now we are not adding one for
the observation but we adding only the
belief that we are in that state to to
the uh to the original alpha and
something similar here where we add the
belief in the
transition more or less
So,
um, yeah, I can imagine that this was a
little bit fast and maybe a little bit
abstract because there were not not so
many examples. But I felt this for the
people who really want to know, okay,
where do these equations come from? I
think this is quite a quite a relevant
contribution. And um so what I was
talking about now was only this X's and
Zs. The notes are still there,
right? Yeah. Great.
Um and now we want to translate this to
this setting where we are actually uh
having this
S and the A's and the O's. So then the
equations get even a little bit more
complicated. So I thought it was good to
have this build up to first see okay
what is the general principle this mean
field approximation and the dishlay
coming out and then you can apply
exactly the same procedure to this more
complicated setting where we have this
full generative model and then you get
this derivation here which I don't uh
I'm not going into now but there we see
again at the end that we have a
dirishlay
distribution and here you see okay alpha
we have to add this to the alpha we have
to add this to the alpha a we have have
to add this to the alpha b and then we
get so this is the the main part of the
paper
uh we have these uh updates here for the
learning
So um yeah so for the people interested
in uh knowing where do these learning
rules come from
um there is this appendix B which I went
through now a little bit quickly and
maybe little bit high level but
um yeah you can look at that in more
detail or ask me questions about it if
you uh are interested in this and maybe
to just link it to the other literature.
So here there's this is the book of
Thomas Far. There's his appendix B23
learning and here he is coming to the
same
uh equations but using a bit different
method that I found hard to follow. So
uh yeah but these these update rules
they are also
here and uh the same
also in this paper. Let's see if the
reference. Yeah. So here we also have
these uh updates but also using a
different method than the one I'm using
and actually this method that I am
presenting is referred to me by Connor
Hines. So thanks very much for uh
pointing me to this derivation because I
think this for me at least is the most
clear one I have seen so far.
[Music]
Um yeah so so far about
uh
learning so there's one I would be able
to if there are time allows could go
briefly over the appendix A but maybe we
also first take some time to uh for
questions about this learning part and
I'm also fine with not discussing uh
this appendix Hey,
awesome. Okay, I will uh ask some
questions that were submitted by Arun
and then if anyone else has any
questions, they can go for
it. Okay, first question. Do you intend
the accompanying repository to be a
static accompaniment to the paper or do
you see it evolving? for example, adding
habitual policy selection to the agent
via e tensor.
[Music]
Um I would say from my side
uh I'm not really planning on uh
developing it further but uh if people
want to I am very happy for example if
they fork the repository copy it in any
way would be nice if you reference me if
you still use it but um yeah so from my
side I don't see any further
developments ments uh but I would be
very happy if other people want to
actively start using it. So please get
in touch if you want to. Cool. Okay.
Would it be possible to further document
the flattening class at first with
comments but ideally with unit tests?
Yeah. So that is indeed so uh maybe a
good point to make about the the code.
So um in PIMDP
uh there is some I have that also here
in appendix C I
think. Uh
some yeah there is some extra
um kind of structure being put on for
example these uh um these conditional
probability distribution. So for example
we say the location in the N next time
step is independent of the reward
condition in the previous time step and
that is for the computations it's very
nice because the computations get a bit
uh
easier but
um the code gets a lot more complicated
and you don't see especially because for
example here.
Um, if we look at all these,
uh, for example, get believe next
states. Yeah, I think that's a good
example. Update belief current state.
Something like
this. Um, for example, this
one. Um, this is very simple and
elegant. I would say and that is because
I am ignoring that so to say in the code
that that there exist these
independencies and I did that uh uh on
purpose just to keep the code as simple
as
possible. But what is then a bit harder
is that so
um
so what uh PIM MDP is
using is
um having some kind of
state which is somehow uh
multi-dimensional and then also for
example uh the A matrix let's say which
um is also has is I think some kind of
uh list so and the observation state so
there's observation modality state
factor so these are both have can have
multiple uh elements so this is a list
of matrices and these
matrices so for each modalities Let's
say it's modality
m and um this is then again um some kind
of tensor where we have here the
uh observations for that specific
modality. But then we still have here
uh
also for every state factor
uh a different um dimension so to say
and in my case what I am doing is just
saying okay we just say that we the
state space is let's say
onedimensional and we just have uh s1
one
one s uh one two let's say there's two
state vectors and I'm just putting them
all into a long list so to say so that's
what I call flattening and then this a
matrix is just one matrix where there's
all the the flattened states here let's
say S
flat and here O
flat and that makes the the code very
easy. But there there I do need
something to translate between the pi
and dp states which are somehow have
these different state factors and the
flat states that I am
using and that is indeed I agree is not
uh uh the best documented code. So, I I
wrote that and then I tucked it away in
this flattening
uh class and was hoping that everyone
would believe me that uh it works well.
But we could talk about it because I do
think it's uh a good point that it would
be nice if it has like uh if you don't
just have to believe me that it works,
but that you can actually check it
yourself. So maybe we can you can send
me an email and we can discuss how to
best uh to best document it.
Yeah, lots of uh little challenges with
matrix format and yeah, small things
that uh yeah, definitely. Okay, I'll ask
Erin's last last uh question here and
this is kind of a good uh final
discussion piece which is what do you
see as the next key area to tackle in
terms of increasing the clarity of how
active inference
works?
Hm. Yeah, that's an interesting
question. So, I felt that with this
paper,
most of the questions I had were
answered.
Um I'm now looking a bit uh together
with uh Lance Tak Costa also at how well
for example these learning rules in
practice are actually
performing. Um but that is maybe
different from
uh from so I feel at least in my opinion
in the paper it's clear how they are
formulated so I would
say
yeah I would be open for suggestions but
I so I have answered with this paper
most of the questions at least I at
about how active inference works and
then then of course about this very
specific domain of the discrete time uh
domain. Yeah. What what did you uh think
or have any conversations about how this
relates to the continuous and the
path-based versions?
So I have actually only spent time with
the
discrete setting. So um I was I think in
the beginning very optimistic. I thought
okay first understand the discrete and
then the
continuous but then I first spent time
on understanding it and then I thought
okay let me write this paper on it which
also took quite some time. So I actually
have no experience with the continuous
case. I'm not sure L Lens is not here
right or no otherwise we could ask him
but he is more familiar with so I think
that's more a question for him maybe he
is at some way able to answer that at
some point
cool what are your next steps or how are
you going to move forward having
satisfyingly reduced your uncertainty
about discrete states
yeah so I am very interested in general
in this
uh we could maybe call it AB learning uh
domain. So how is an agent actually
learning these uh matrices? So uh
together with Carlotta with my colleague
we were also applying this framework to
study uh consciousness or we're still
busy with that and a paper about it
hopefully coming out soon where we uh
use an active inference agent and then
look at how it's um integrated
information is uh uh
developing and uh Um but we saw actually
in the environment that we were using
that it was very hard for the agent to
learn the A and B matrices or learn an A
and B matrices that allows it to uh
operate well in the environment. So for
me that's the next big question is how
what is actually are these learning
rules from active inference the right
ones or are there other rules that are
maybe more effective and maybe more
probable. So that is for me a big
question that I completely don't have an
answer to right now but this really I
find really fascinating.
Awesome. Any other comments you'd like
to make?
Um so I think it's good to finish it
here but just to to say that it's there
is there's also this appendix A. So
maybe a bit weirdly but the uh I think
all of free energy and active inference
usually is formulated as a minimization
of this variation of free energy.
But starting the story from there I find
then it gets very confusing uh most of
the time. But I do write here in
appendix A how everything that's written
in this paper can also be related to
uh to this bigger idea of minimizing an
variational free energy function. So you
can just read through it here.
perception, learning and action
selection, how they are all related to
minimizing
dysfunction. Just so you know that it's
there.
Awesome. Well, again, thank you for the
important and
pedagogical work. I I look forward to
many in this genre.
Thank you so much for the opportunity.
And uh again if anyone is has has any
questions or wants to reach out please
uh feel free to do so. Awesome. Thank
you. See you. Thank you.